Hello everyone and welcome
to EnglishPod, my name is Marco.
My name is Catherine and we're
going to a family party today right Marco.
That's right we're going
to go see our family,
our relatives and we're
going to talk about
all the different family
members that you
can have so there's
some very specific family
members that sometimes you
don't really know the names of.
That's right so we're
not talking about
mother, father, brother,
sister, we're talking
about what we call in
English extended family
so that means not
just the people you live
with but also people
you're related to who
are maybe in different
parts of your family.
That's right so let's listen to our
dialogue and we'll be back in a bit.
What are you doing this weekend?
My brother-in-law is having a small get
together at his house and he invited me.
Is it a family thing or just friends?
A bit of both, some
cousins and some uncles
will be there but also some
friends from the neighborhood.
Is your great uncle Rick going to be there?
He is really funny.
Yeah he's going to be there
with his stepson and his ex-wife.
You mean your sister?
No Rick is actually my great uncle
so he's my grandmother's brother.
You lost me.
A hug's fun later.
Let's go.
All right so now let's talk about these
family members on language takeaway.
So Marko we've got four
family members to talk
about today and the
first one is brother-in-law.
Right so we have the
word brother-in-law so
basically this person is
married to your sister.
That's right so I have
a brother, I have a
sister but when these
people marry, they
marry someone who I'm
not related to by blood.
We call them in-law so
brother-in-law, sister-in-law.
Right so that's exactly it.
The key there is that when it has the ending
in-law it means that you're not related
to them by blood it's your
extended family because of marriage.
That's right so I have a
younger brother when
he gets married I will
have a sister-in-law.
That's right and it
applies to for example
father-in-law that would
be your husband's dad
or mother-in-law would
be your husband's mother.
Yeah so these are all
related to you by marriage.
All right so now moving on to
the next type of extended family
member that we have is a
step-son, your uncle has a step-son.
So a step-son now this can get very
confusing let's take a simple, simple family.
Mm-hmm.
We have two people and they're married but
they get divorced so they split up and now
maybe they had some kids, the wife has
kids and she gets married to someone else.
Mm-hmm.
So her new husband
calls her son his step-son.
Right.
Because it's not his son it's another man's
son but they're still related by marriage.
So when your new
husband or your new wife
has kids from another marriage
they're called step-son, step daughter.
That's right so it's the same thing as if
my mother got divorced and she remarried,
she has a new husband, that
man would be my step-father.
All right so these are
all family members when
you hear the word step, family
members that we have because of divorce.
Mm-hmm.
So step-son, step-daughter,
step-father, step-mother, all right.
And now again related
to the whole divorce thing
the person that you get divorced to
is called an ex-wife or an ex-husband.
All right so ex-girlfriend or
ex-boyfriend means previous.
Mm-hmm.
So my ex-wife is someone I was married
to before or in the case of a woman.
My ex-husband was
someone I was married to
before but we got divorced
so we're not married now.
That's exactly it.
So it only applies to a
husband and wife, right?
You don't say my ex-children
or my ex-mother-in-law.
Well because your children
are always your children.
All right.
Exactly.
If you talk about your
ex-wife's parents, you
just say my ex-wife's
father or my ex-wife's
mother because there's no more
in-law, there's no law, you're not married.
Right, okay.
And lastly now we have an uncle but just
not any uncle, we have our great uncle.
Great uncle.
So they actually explain
this in the dialogue,
they say he is my
grandmother's brother.
Right.
Okay, so my uncle, this is simple.
My uncle is my mother's brother
or my father's brother, easy.
But my great uncle is one
of my grandparents' brothers.
Right.
So my grandmother's brother
or my grandfather's brother.
Right.
In English we don't distinguish.
We don't say a different word for
grandmother's brother or grandfather's brother.
Right, right exactly.
So your great uncle could be either your
grandmother's brother or your grandfather's
brother.
That's right.
I have, well, I just have one
great uncle and one great aunt.
My grandmother has
a sister so I have a great
aunt and my grandfather has a
brother so I have a great uncle.
And now the prefix
"great" can also be
applied for example to grandparents
so you can say my great grandfather.
That's right.
So we're talking about generations.
I have a grandfather but his
father is my great grandfather.
That means we go back in
the past one more generation.
That's right.
All right so let's take a break and
let's listen to the dialogue again.
My brother-in-law is having a small
get-together at his house and he invited me.
Is it a family thing or just friends?
A bit of both.
Some cousins and
some uncles will be there
but also some friends
from the neighborhood.
Is your great uncle Rick going to be there?
He is really funny.
Yeah, he's going to be there
with his stepson and his ex-wife.
You mean your sister?
No, Rick is actually my great uncle
so he's my grandmother's brother.
You lost me.
A hug's fun later.
Let's go.
All right we're back so we've
picked out three key phrases for you.
Let's take a look at those
now on Fluency Builder.
Fluency Builder.
All right so on Fluency Builder
we have a great noun here actually.
We might have heard
this before in a different
way but in today's dialogue we're
talking about a small get-together.
My brother-in-law is
having a small get-together.
Now what is it get-together more?
Right so as you notice
we say "a" get-together
meaning that get-together we are taking it
as a noun and it may be confusing because
you see the verb "get"
and you're thinking
it's a verb but no "a" get-together
is a reunion, a meeting.
All right a party, a party.
So maybe it's a very informal
party, very casual, not fancy.
I get-together I could say Marco.
I'm having a get-together at my apartment,
do you want to come and bring a girlfriend?
Right so very simple maybe we have a
drink or some food but it's nothing fancy.
That's right very informal,
very casual, a get-together.
And when we were asking
about the get-together
we asked if it's a family
thing or is it just friends?
So I want to take a look at
this phrase here, a family thing.
Is it a family thing?
What am I asking when I say okay Marco?
This party you're having,
is it a family thing?
Well you're asking if it's a
family reunion, a family party.
So that means if I'm not in
your family can I still come?
Right.
Right because if it's a family thing
it's just for people in my family.
Right, right.
If it's for everyone no problem
but I don't want to go to
your house if it's a family
thing because that's private.
Right so usually for
example maybe Christmas
dinner would usually
be a family thing, you
celebrate it with your family mostly but
you know it's not always a family thing.
That's what I could say.
This year my birthday is just a family
thing, I'm only inviting family members.
Exactly.
All right and lastly we got a little bit
confused with the great uncle and the step
sign and the ex-wife and so we said
you know what, you lost me, you lost me.
You lost me.
Now this is another great phrase, the phrase
means I don't understand, I'm confused.
Right, that's exactly it.
So if someone is explaining
something and I don't understand
then you can say you know what
you lost me, I don't understand.
Right and sometimes I
say this when someone is
giving a very long
explanation for something
so to get to my house, you turn left here
and then you go two blocks, you turn right
and you go straight and
you wait for the stoplight
and then you go to the right hand corner,
there's a store, I say wait, wait, wait.
You lost me.
Right, exactly.
I don't understand.
I'm confused, that's right.
All right so that's all we have, let's
listen to the dialogue one last time.
What are you doing this weekend?
My brother-in-law is having a small get
together at his house and he invited me.
Is it a family thing or just friends?
A bit of both.
Some cousins and
some uncles will be there,
but also some friends
from the neighborhood.
Is your great uncle Rick going to be there?
He is really funny.
Yeah, he's going to be there
with his stepson and his ex-wife.
You mean your sister?
No, Rick is actually my great uncle
so he's my grandmother's brother.
You lost me.
A hug's fun later, let's go.
So speaking of extended family
members, what else can we mention?
We have a step family, your
stepson, your stepdaughter.
What about if you have an adopted child,
would you say, would you differentiate it?
Some people do, some
people don't, most people
just say this is my son,
this is my daughter.
But I would like to
add that with stepson,
stepdaughter, it's not just
divorce that we have this.
Also, if the parent,
the parent, maybe the
mother dies and the
father has a new wife, then
the new wife can say this is my
stepson, this is my stepdaughter.
So there are two
possibilities, one is death
and one is remarriage
because of divorce.
Right.
As far as adopted,
no, usually just say my
son and my daughter,
but I can tell you this.
If my father and my
mother divorce, my father
has a new wife, and
together they have a baby,
the baby boy or girl
is my half-brother or
half-sister because we
share one parent, my father.
Yeah, this is very
interesting, so if you
do have a brother or
sister that is not from
your same mother
or father, but just one
parent, then yeah, it's
called a half-brother or sister.
Half, remember this, half because half of
their parents are the same as your parents.
Right.
Maybe one father or
mother, but with step
brothers and step sisters,
the only reason you're
related is because of
marriage, because of blood.
We didn't mention
that you could have step
brother, so it's your
brother, but he's legally
your brother, but he's not related to
your father or anyone in your family.
That's right, that's
right, so maybe you have
many step brothers,
you could have a step
brother and a half
brother, so there are lots
of different combinations
because of many different reasons.
All right, guys, that's
all the time we have
for today, but it's a little
bit of a confusing topic.
Have any questions or any doubts
you can come to our website, englishpod.
com, and you can
leave them there.
We hope to see you guys
online and until next time, bye!